77% of the people in India are victims of a secret disease.
This disease is ravaging 77% of the population, which means three out of four people, and is causing
blood pressure, diabetes, and even
heart attacks at a young age. This disease
is the disease of taking tension. Tension means stress.
In the coming 20 years,
stress will be the biggest killer in the country.
Despite having an active life style, recently
Nitin Kamat of Jaroda suffered a minor stroke.
Exhaustion, dehydration and poor sleep could be some of the
reasons. Let me tell you about my close examples.
At the age of 28, my friend's
hair has turned completely white due to stress. At the
age of 32, my college senior has to
take insulin injections.
Doctors say that the reason for this is
stress. And after the pandemic,
how many of us have seen cases of high blood
pressure, heart attacks and early cancer around us?
I've lost count. Today we will tell you
one such statistic. You get
excessive tension over small things.
You lie in bed at night and start
overthinking.  We keep doing this and after waking up in the morning, we feel like
why am I even alive. So
this video is for you because we will
not only talk about problems but also about solutions.
We will break down this video into three parts.
First, we will understand
why stress happens, then its
effect on your body, and then we will
understand some secrets and techniques that can help you
reduce your stress. If you like this video and
learn something new and interesting, then don't forget to subscribe to the channel.
Many of you
like watching videos but have
forgotten to subscribe to the channel. It
is free for you, but it helps us a lot.
In 2022, when we got Covid in the month of January,
we were
unable to create content for two months, could not focus,
and this started causing us additional stress.
We all say health is wealth,
but we do not understand when a small
illness becomes a serious problem.
Nowadays,
things like cardiac arrest and stroke are occurring in people of 30-40 years of age. Is
this right happening to our
bodies?  We make them work like machines,
but we don't treat our bodies the same way we care for a machine and get it
serviced periodically.
We don't do anything until we're completely overwhelmed, and
then we end up visiting hospitals and
paying exorbitant bills for months. Getting food home
delivered is easy, but can
reducing our mental and physical stress be just as
easy? We believe it's
possible. That's why we want to educate
you about preventative healthcare with Apollo ProHealth.
Apollo runs India's most
personalized health assessment program,
focused on preventative healthcare.
In preventative healthcare, you undergo a risk assessment
before you develop an illness, not after,
to determine your
chances of developing heart problems. Whether
you have any hidden diseases or
how we can prevent cancer before it occurs,
expert
doctors help you with all these things. Apollo has 25
million healthcare checks and 40 years of
experience. With the help of AI, Apollo can
predict your future health risks.  This allows
you to make necessary lifestyle
modifications today. You are
assigned a health mentor, meaning
with the help of doctors, you can prevent future problems like diabetes, hypertension,
cardiac arrest, and even cancer
today.
Especially for women, mammography and
Pap smear tests are life-saving
because if cancer is detected early, the
chances of it progressing to a complete cancer are
very high. All these tests
are available in ProHealth to ensure you stay safe.
Keep your body healthy with Apollo ProHealth.
Prevent diseases before they occur, and make your life better
and longer. Let's Be ProHealth.
Chapter One: Why Stress Happens? Let's
start with a very controversial statement: "
Stress is good for humans." Is
stress good? During the CA final
exam, when the paper was still pending and only
five minutes were left, what did you know about the stress you felt at that time?
Let me
explain. Stress
is good for human evolution, or not? Because stress makes
us alert.
This small, almond-shaped part of our brain is
triggered.  Which we call Amak Dila
which also triggers fight or flight response.
Earlier, on seeing any threat like snake,
leopard or tiger,
we were able to survive due to stress. Just like a deer has the
capability to defeat even the world's fastest cheetah, similarly if the super human
survival instinct did not give us stress
then what is the problem? The problem is that
in today's times, how many of us have to face
real threats, how many have to
spend the night in the jungle, how many have to
remain alert to stay alive, I
feel that no one watching this video has this. There are
no life threatening threats in today's modern life, but no one has told this to your brain.
This habit of taking stress which has been there for generations has not gone away, so
we always start looking for threats in our environment. I am getting laid off,
I have been laid off, exams are coming,
studies are not over, I missed the train, I did
not get promotion, I came back to Australia in the finals of T-20 World Cup,
That's right, there
's the problem. Our brain
doesn't understand the difference between actual life threats and our perceived threats. The real lion is
temporary. Because of stress, the
lion living in our mind can tear us apart at any time. The
problem arises when this
mental stress starts affecting our physical body.
Chapter Two: The Physical
Impact of Stress. Okay, in the first part of the video,
we learned how stress
served an important purpose for humanity,
but today stress has become a disease.
Let's look at the data and understand how
these five diseases can be caused by stress.
Number four of these was really
shocking for me too. Number five: Impact
on your heart.
This research from Nature Reviews Cardiology says that
employees who work in a very stressful environment and are
socially isolated,
their first heart attack or stroke is
due to stress. The
chances of heart attack due to stress are
40 to 50.  During the pandemic,
famous people like Puneet Rajkumar, Siddharth Shukla, Raju Srivastava, Raj Kaushal
lost their lives at an early age. We think
that if we live a healthy and active lifestyle,
we will not have any problems. So,
note that Saif Ali Khan had
a minor heart attack in 2007 when
he was only 36 years old. This means that we have to
understand that there are many such things happening inside our body
whose effects are not visible outside.
Number four: Impact on your immune system. Did you know that
stress makes it
difficult to fight AIDS. Understand this:
HIV is a sexually transmitted
disease. You do not get AIDS due to stress,
but due to stress, the
impact of AIDS on your body increases rapidly
because basically both AIDS and
stress impact your immunity. There is
no cure for HIV,
but with medical advancements, we
can keep the virus count low in our body
and live a long life,
of course, if we do not take stress about it.
Number three: Your weight  But the impact, as
we saw in Chapter One, is that stress puts
us into survival mode.
Whenever a crisis occurs, the
first thing our body does is strive for
more energy than sufficient, meaning
food. Stress-eating is real.
During times of stress, we feel more hungry. The interesting
thing is that in the short run, stress
burns fat and we lose weight, so
we feel we need to eat more. However,
in chronic stress, the
emotional side of our brain is triggered, and
we start eating calorie-dense foods like
chocolates, ice cream, or something else. The
WHO says that
more than 50 grams of sugar is harmful for any human being,
which is quite a lot of sugar. Now you
might say, "How can I eat that much sugar in a day?" So,
watch this video on sugar. Your eyes will be opened. Number
two, the impact on your hair. This doctor is
a professor at Harvard. He conducted
an experiment on rats. He
put them in stressful situations in short bursts. The result was a change in their hair
color.  Stress
increases the amount of cortisol in our body.
Stress permanently damages our hair follicles
and in a way,
stress is also responsible for premature aging. There are
some people who
look 40 even at the age of 30, and some
people look 30 even at the age of 50.
Stress has the number one impact on your sexual health.
For women, there
is a deep connection between stress and menstruation. Without
stress, our body produces estrogen and
progesterone. Their proper
balance is necessary for timely periods.
Due to stress, the HPA gets activated
and the body feels that
this is not the right time to conceive a child.
Complications can occur. Stress is
dangerous not only for you but also for your unborn child.
Due to stress, women may also experience painful periods.
PCOS gets
aggravated due to stress and
many other problems can arise due to stress.
Decreased testosterone levels in men,
erectile dysfunction, lower libido, and even
obesity are considered stress-related diseases.
If you
want to read about these in detail, all the links are on
our
YouTube channel. Related chest pain, even
increased chances of cancer. Let's move on to the
most important part of the video. Let's
understand some small things
that can help you control stress.
Chapter Three: How to Beat Stress. Okay, so
what's the solution? Aditi Nerurkar tells
a very interesting story in her book, The Five Resets.
She says
that in ancient times, coal miners would take
a singing bird with them underground in the mines
and listen to its song.
But when the bird stopped singing, they would
leave their work and return to the ground with the bird. The
reason is that the bird would
sing as long as it got sufficient oxygen. When the
amount of oxygen in the air decreased, the
bird would stop singing, and the miners would
receive a signal.  It is known that working now is dangerous.
We need to look for these signals, which are
different for every person. For
example, sweat is an excellent sign.
Healthy human sweat should be odorless.
Sweat odor is caused by bacteria
or stress because normal
sweat comes from these glands, and stress-
related sweat also comes from these glands. So, I can tell
if your body is odorous when you come home after working all day in AC,
which means the day was
stressful. You have to observe your own patterns and see
when the
stress is going out of your control.
A theme of this entire video has been that in modern day
life, whatever causes us stress
seems much bigger than it actually is. Whenever you feel stressed about something,
remember this number: 10 10 10. Think
whether this thing will cause you stress after 10 minutes.
Think whether this thing will cause you stress after 10 months.
Think whether this thing will cause you
stress after 10 years. School marks matter.  It is
very easy to say no, but at that time,
in that situation, the pressure of exams is so much
that everyone asks, everyone compares, so it is
natural to get stressed. Will my
saying anything relieve your stress? Otherwise,
look around you,
scan the people around you,
scan the celebrities and think, do you judge them on the basis of
how many marks they got in the 12th standard? Do
you recognize them because of their marks?
Remember that after 10 years, no one will
remember your marks. So, study
honestly, but stop worrying about marks. At
work, when there is an
important presentation and suddenly the
laptop screen does not connect, then you get
stressed, but the self-life of this stress is
only 10 minutes, after 10 months you do
not remember it. Similarly, while driving,
if you miss a U-turn, then there is
another U-turn ahead. A few minutes are
definitely wasted, maybe you get late in reaching the office too,
but this stress is only a
momentary tension. Life does not end
if you keep watching this video till the end.
So I feel it is my
responsibility to
share with you all the solutions that
helped me a lot. Take a paper and
divide it into three parts: 10 minutes, 10 months,
and 10 years. Write down all the things that are giving you tension.
Divide them and give each one as much
importance as you want.
After this list is made,
hold all the answers in front of yourself and ask yourself, is
any of these things important enough to turn my hair
grey forever? Is
any of these things important enough to give me
diabetes at the age of 32? Is
any of these things
important enough to make me sick? No, then
take a deep breath and let it go. Since childhood, I used to think that
solutions to very difficult problems should be very difficult.
Actually, this is false.
Solutions to difficult problems are easy, but easy
solutions are effective only when they are
implemented with complete honesty. There is a technique
called PMR Progressive Muscle
Relaxation, in which you relax each muscle one by one.  Tense the body
and then relax it. You have to
start from the toes. Hold the toes tightly as
if the earth is slipping from under the feet
and then slowly release them. Do the
same thing with the wrists, hips
and in the same way
slowly come up. Do meditation for the mind.
Exercise for the body and to
detect the upcoming problems of your body in advance, do regular
preventive health checkup. Not all at once,
gradually, not just one day, but every day. You have to
become better. You have to make your body
your partner and not your enemy. You have to be
aware of your body. You have to stay healthy and do
not keep tension in your mind
because a great man has said
not to take tension but to give tension and it makes a
difference to me if I convey this important message to you
[Music]